<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Getting Started</title>
      <author email="jddixon@users.sourceforge.net">Jim Dixon</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Getting Started">
      <p>There are basically two ways to get Quilt - and most other open
      source software.  The first is CVS, which gives you access to 
      last night's version of the code.  The second is to download the 
      latest release.  This is more likely to work, but is less up to date;
      current plans are to put out incremental Quilt 0.6a releases at 
      roughly 2 week intervals.</p>
      
      <p>Quilt is being developed on systems running Linux and FreeBSD.
        If you are working under a Microsoft operating system, you may
        need to use some initiative to get the advice that follows to
        work.  We will try to improve on this situation; please be 
        patient.</p>
      
      <subsection name="CVS Access">
        <p>Quilt is hosted on 
          <a href="http://www.sourceforge.net">SourceForge.</a>
          On Unix systems, 
          you can get a copy of the most recent version of Quilt by
          typing:
        </p>
<source><![CDATA[
cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/quilt checkout quilt-dev 
]]></source>
        <p>This will deliver the very latest version to your desktop,
          creating a <b>quilt-dev</b> subdirectory in the current 
          directory.</p>

        <p>If you are using another operating system, or have trouble
          with the instructions above, try 
          <a href="http://sourceforge.net/docman/display_doc.php?docid=14033&amp;group_id=1">Sourceforge's CVS documentation</a>;
          this is lucid and reasonably easy to follow.</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Downloads">
        <p>The alternative is downloading a tarball.  This is very
          simple indeed.  You should see a <b>Download</b> button at
          the top of this Web page; if you click on it, it will take
          you to Quilt's Sourceforge download page.  The most recent
          tarballs will be listed towards the top.  If you just want
          to use Quilt, get the binary distribution, which will have
          a name like <code>quilt-0.6-a1-bin.tar.gz</code>.  If you 
          want the source code, so that you can see how it works,
          you will need the source distribution, which has a name like
          <code>quilt-0.6-a1-src.tar.gz</code>.</p>
          
            <p>Javadocs are included with the binary distribution and
              built by the source distribution.</p>

          <p>Click on whichever 
          you prefer, and your browser will get it for you.</p>

        <p>Once you have the tarball, put it in the directory where
          you want your Quilt subdirectory and type </p>
<source><![CDATA[
  tar -vzxf quilt*gz
]]></source>
        <p>and it will be extracted for you.  <em>(These instructions 
            are of course suitable for Linux/Unix hosts; if you are 
            using Windows, you need to adjust appropriately.)</em></p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Where's the Jar?">
        <p>Either of the procedures above will give you a distribution
          in a subdirectory with a name like <code>quilt-0.6-a1</code>.
          If you have the binary distribution, in that directory you 
          will find a Quilt jar; in this case it would be 
          <code>quilt-0.6-a1.jar</code>.  If you have the source 
          distribution, you can build the jar by typing</p>
<source><![CDATA[
  ant jar
]]></source>
        <p>This will create a Quilt jar in the <code>target</code> 
          subdirectory.</p>

      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Confidence Building">
        <p>You can now actually use Quilt by copying the Quilt jar
          into the <b>example</b> directory and then moving into one
          of the directories below hat.  For example, the following
          commands will copy the jar, take you into the 
          <code>example/3x6</code> directory, and build and run the 
          tests:</p>
<source><![CDATA[
  cp quilt*jar example
  cd example/3x6
  ant test
]]></source>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="For Developers">
        <p>Those with an interest in Quilt's inner workings are advised 
        to get the software using CVS.  There are currently several 
        file changes a day.</p>

      <p>Once you have the software, you should go into the base
        Quilt directory and run the tests.</p>  
      
<source><![CDATA[
  cd quilt
  ant test
]]></source>
      <p>These should execute with no or very few errors.  If you
        do see serious errors, it is likely that there are problems
        with the installation.</p>

      <p>The most likely problems are classpath errors and missing
        jar files.</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
