<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Quilt Glossary</title>
      <author email="jddixon@users.sourceforge.net">Jim Dixon</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Quilt Glossary">
      <font color="darkblue">
        <p><em>For more Extreme Programming acronyms, see the
          <a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?XpGlossary">Xp Glossary</a>.
         A few of the explanations there are fanciful, though.</em></p></font>

      <table>
        <tr><th>word</th><th>definition</th></tr>

        <tr><td>Ant</td><td>A utility for managing Java builds, probably
            the most widely used in the world. See
            <a href="http://ant.apache.org">ant.apache.org</a>. </td></tr>

        <tr><td>bcel</td><td>The 
            <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org"> 
              <b>Byte Code Engineering Library</b> </a>
            is an <a href="http://www.apache.org">Apache</a> project,
            software for manipulating Java at the bytecode level.  Bcel
            is used extensively in Quilt.
        </td></tr>
        
        <tr><td>bytecode</td><td>The 'machine language' interpreted by
            the <b>JVM.</b></td></tr>
       
        <tr><td>coverage</td><td>A measure of the extent to which test
            programs exercise the software under test, usually 
            expressed as a percentage (this being, for example, the
            number of lines of code that were executed during the test
            vs the total number of lines of code).</td></tr>

        <tr><td>Extreme Programming</td><td>Or <b>XP</b>.  A lightweight
            programming methodology.  For more information see, for 
            example, Ron Jeffries' <a href="http://www.xprogramming.com">
              XProgramming.com</a> Web site.</td></tr>

        <tr><td>hit count</td><td>The number of times a unit of code
            has been executed.</td></tr>

        <tr><td>instrumentation</td><td><b>Bytecode,</b> variables, 
            and methods inserted into 
            a Java class to collect information on or modify
            program behavior.  <b>Coverage</b> is usually measured by
            instrumenting methods with bytecode that collects hit 
            counts.</td></tr>

        <tr><td>integration test</td><td>A test that software modules
            work together as expected.  <b>JUnit</b> was designed 
            specifically for unit testing, but can be used in integration 
            testing, as can Quilt.</td></tr>
        
        <tr><td>JUnit</td><td>A unit testing program for Java, probably
            the most widely used.  See
            <a href="http://www.junit.org">www.junit.org</a>. </td></tr>
        
        <tr><td>JVM</td><td>The Java Virtual Machine, a program which
            executes <b>bytecode</b>.  The JVM is a simple stack machine
            with a limited instruction set.</td></tr>

        <tr><td>Maven</td><td>A Java project management tool integrating
            many other open-source Java tools.  
            <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven</a> can be used to 
            manage builds, automatically generating and running Ant 
            <code>build.xml</code> files, but is most commonly used
            for generating project Web sites.</td></tr>

        <tr><td>mock objects</td><td>An object that has the same 
            interface as a production class, but whose functionality
            is limited to (a) verifying that parameters supplied are correct
            and (b) faking the normal responses of the object being
            mocked to the degree necessary to allow it to be 
            substituted for it.  In a JUnit testing environment, a 
            mock object will throw an exception when input verification
            fails.<br/>
            There is a surprising degree of 
            disagreement about the exact definition of this term.
            For one set of opinions see <a href="http://www.mockobjects.com">
              www.mockobjects.com</a>
        </td></tr>
        
        <tr><td>q$$q</td><td>One of a number of Quilt-reserved names.<br/>
            <code>public static int[] <b>q$$q</b></code> is the
            hit count array generated by Quilt-instrumented classes
            as run time.<br/>
            <code>public static int q$$qID</code> is a run-unique ID
            assigned to a Quilt-instrumented class.<br/>
            <code>public static int q$$qVer</code> is the Quilt 
            file format, currently 0, construed as 0.0 (16-bit major
            value, 16-bit minor value).
        </td></tr>

        <tr><td>regression test</td><td>A test or set of tests that 
          verifies that software still behaves correctly after being
          changed.  Normally, the suite of unit tests and integration 
          tests developed with the software are accumulated and used for
          regression testing in code maintainance or further software
          development.</td></tr>

        <tr><td>spy</td><td>A class or method that mimics an object
            under test, but whose only function is to report on values
            observed.  So a spy is a somewhat elaborated <b>stub</b>
            or degenerate <b>mock object.</b></td></tr>

      <tr><td>stub</td><td>A class or method that has the same interface as
          the class/method under test, but in effect no functionality 
          at all.  A class consisting of empty methods, or a method 
          that does nothing if void or otherwise just returns a fixed
          value.  A stub might be considered a degenerate 
          <b>mock object.</b></td></tr>
      
      <tr><td>test-driven development</td><td>An incremental approach to 
              software development in which writing tests precedes 
              writing the software being tested. See 
<a href="http://www.objectmentor.com/writeUps/TestDrivenDevelopment">this article</a>
            for a brief introduction.
          </td></tr>

        <tr><td>transformation</td><td>In most discussions involving 
            Quilt, this is a <b>sense-preserving transformation,</b>
            a change to Java-related software which has no effect on 
            its normal functionality.  Usually the change involves adding 
            <b>instrumentation</b> to the software which allows 
            side effects (measurements such as <b>hit counts</b>) 
            to be collected at runtime.
        </td></tr>

        <tr><td>unit test</td><td>A test of software at the lowest
            level of modularity; a test of an individual class or method
            as opposed to a test of a system consisting of many 
            interacting classes.  Software development methodologies 
            such as <b>Extreme Programming (XP)</b> and <b>Test-Driven 
              Development</b> emphasize 
            the development of software and unit tests as one process, 
            or go even further, encouraging programmers to write tests 
            before writing the software.</td></tr>
        
        <tr><td>VM</td><td>See <b>JVM.</b></td></tr>

        <tr><td>XP</td><td>See <b>Extreme Programming.</b></td></tr>

      </table>


      <!-- keep at the bottom -->
      <hr/>
        <em>This material is copyright 2003 by James David Dixon 
        ("Jim Dixon") and is made available under the 
        <a href="community/artistic-license.html">Artistic License</a>.</em>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
      
