<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Quilt</title>
      <author email="jddixon@users.sourceforge.net">Jim Dixon</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Quilt">
      <p>
        <em>Quilt</em> is a Java software development tool that measures 
        <b>coverage</b>, the extent to which unit testing exercises the 
        software under test.  It is optimized for use with the 
        <a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit</a> 
        unit test package, the 
        <a href="http://ant.apache.org">Ant</a>
        Java build facility, and the 
        <a href="http://www.maven.org">Maven</a> 
        project management toolkit.
      
        </p><p>Quilt is currently undergoing a major transformation.  
        The first release of the new version, 0.6a, became available 
        on 31 August 2003.  This is now forking off as a separate 
        project while development of the 0.4/0.5 branch will continue
        at Codehaus.  More on the changes in progress 
        <a href="#0.6a">below.</a>
        
      </p><p>This is the Quilt 0.6a Web site.  
        <font color="red">The earlier <b>Quilt 0.4</b> Web site is available 
        <a href="/quilt-0.4">here.</a> </font>
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Coverage">
      <p> The primary aim of the Quilt Project is the development of tools
        for measuring coverage in the testing of Java programs.
        Coverage is a measure of the extent to which tests exercise the
        code under test.

        </p><p> The simplest measure of coverage is statement coverage.
        For example, if there are 100 lines in a program and only 75 are
        actually used when tests are being run, then the coverage may be
        said to be 75%.  
        
        </p><p> This is a simple but very significant check on the testing
        being done.  If 75% of the code is covered, then 25% isn't: 
        <em>you don't know whether 25% of your application works</em>.
        
        </p><p>Quilt's coverage tools can't actually help you write 
        better tests or better code.  But they <em>can</em> tell you 
        whether or not your code is being tested.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="How It Works">
      <p>Quilt intercepts code as it is being loaded and
        alters it.  It doesn't work at the source code level.  It
        manipulates compiled <em>classes</em> and their <em>bytecode</em>, 
        the machine code of the Java Virtual Machine, the JVM.
        </p><p>To measure coverage, Quilt inserts <em>instrumentation</em>,
        typically bytecode that increments counters whenever a block of
        code or branch is executed.  This is done transparently.  The
        programmer simply sets a switch at test time.  Then when 
        program modules are loaded for testing, Quilt instrumentation 
        is automatically added and coverage reports generated.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Using Quilt with Other Software Development Tools">
      <p>The current version of Quilt is used with the JUnit unit test
        program.  Typically you will run unit tests under they succeed.
        Then, when the debugging is largely done, you run Quilt coverage 
        checks as well
        as JUnit unit tests. If the Quilt run shows that you need more testing, 
        if coverage is too low, 
        you add more tests or alter the ones that you have until you are
        satisfied with the level of coverage.</p>

      <p>One of the objectives of the Quilt project is 
        <em>full JUnit interoperability</em>,
        in that sense that the interface to Quilt should be a superset
        of the JUnit interface.  If you are used to working with JUnit,
        you should be able to work with Quilt in exactly the same way.
        
        </p><p>Quilt and JUnit can also be used in conjunction with 
        Ant, Java's equivalent of the make command-line build 
        facility.  Quilt's Ant task, the module interfacing Ant with
        Quilt and JUnit is complete and available either via CVS or
        in tarball form. </p>
      
        <p>As you can see from inspecting the Quilt distribution,
        the Maven project management software package has also been
        used in developing Quilt.  Maven is used primarily for Web
        site and project documentation generation.  Quilt is being
        integrated back into Maven as part of the development effort;
        that is, a Quilt goal for Maven is in development.</p>
        
        <p>In the somewhat longer term, we expect to integrate 
        Quilt into other software development packages, in particular 
        into the Eclipse IDE.  However, work on this has not yet
        begun.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Other Applications">
      <p>Quilt does its magic using a variety of tools.  These 
        include</p>
      <ul>
        <li> transforming class loaders, which load a compiled Java
          class and change it in some way, typically while 
          leaving its semantics unchanged</li>
        <li> instrumenting class loaders, a special case of 
          transforming loaders which insert counters and other
          blocks of bytecode for monitoring program behavior</li>
        <li> a class synthesizer, which builds a class at run time,
          from a description, rather than loading it from disk</li>
        <li> tools for generating and modifying method control
          flow graphs</li>
        <li> report generation facilities </li>
      </ul>
      <p>These and other Quilt components can be used to build other 
        tools for monitoring and modifying Java code at run time.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Project Status">
      <p> <a name="0.6a"/>
        At the time of writing, there are three distinct versions of 
        Quilt. Quilt 0.4 has been available for download since 
        mid-June 2002.  <b>quilt</b> on the Sourceforge CVS site is 
        Quilt 0.5a as 
        of August/September 2002.  And <b>quilt-dev</b> in CVS is 
        Quilt 0.6a, which is mostly new code, written along the same
        lines and inspired by the earlier version.</p>

      <p>0.6a5 is the final version of this branch of the code.  
        Quilt 0.4/0.5 development will continue at 
        <a href="http://cvs.codehaus.org/viewcvs.cgi/quilt/?root=codehaus">
          Codehaus</a>, while the 0.6 branch will live on, 
        at least in spirit, at 
        <a href="http://jxcl.sourceforge.net">The JXCL Project</a>
        on Sourceforge.</p>

      <table>
        <tr> <th>version</th><th>form</th><th>link</th><th>when</th> </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a</td><td>CVS</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/quilt/quilt-dev">quilt-dev</a></td>
          <td>now</td>
        </tr>
        
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-5</td><td>binary distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-5-bin.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-5-bin.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>20 October 2003</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-5</td><td>source distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-5-src.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-5-src.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>20 October 2003</td>
        </tr>  
        
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-4</td><td>binary distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-4-bin.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-4-bin.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>16 October 2003</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-4</td><td>source distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-4-src.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-4-src.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>16 October 2003</td>
        </tr> 
        
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-3</td><td>binary distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-3-bin.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-3-bin.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>12 October 2003</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-3</td><td>source distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-3-src.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-3-src.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>12 October 2003</td>
        </tr> 

        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-2</td><td>binary distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-2-bin.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-2-bin.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>12 September 2003</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-2</td><td>source distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-2-src.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-2-src.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>12 September 2003</td>
        </tr>  
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-1</td><td>binary distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-1-bin.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-1-bin.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>31 August 2003</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>0.6a-1</td><td>source distribution, tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.6-a-1-src.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.6-a-1-src.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>31 August 2003</td>
        </tr>  
        <tr>
          <td>0.5a</td><td>CVS</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/quilt/quilt">quilt</a></td>
          <td>now</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>0.4</td><td>tarball</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/quilt/quilt-0.4-src.tar.gz?download">quilt-0.4-src.tar.gz</a></td>
          <td>now</td>
        </tr> 
      </table>

      <p>0.6a1 tarballs became available on
        31 August 2003.  This release contained a fully-functional 
        <code>QuiltTask,</code> allowing JUnit and Quilt to be run 
        from Ant. The <code>QuiltTask</code> and <code>TestRunner</code>
        modules have been thoroughly tested and have no known bugs
        when run without coverage tests.</p>
        
      <p>0.6a4 remains primarily a developer release.  The Quilt 
        classloader and its class transformation framework are 
        connected to the QuiltTask front end.  Simple statement
        coverage reports are generated.  However, there are at least 
        eight significant bugs.  Work on the upcoming 0.6a5 release will
        concentrate on bug fixes rather than code enhancements.</p>
      
      <p>Some users
        may wish to experiment with Quilt's Ant task, test runner, and
        report formatters, which we believe will become a significant 
        improvement on the existing Ant JUnit task.</p>
        
      <p>After a reasonable 
        period of time, when the 0.6 release 
        has been reviewed and proved satisfactory, the various other 
        versions currently found in CVS will be withdrawn to reduce 
        confusion.  This is unlikely to occur before 1 January 2004.
      </p>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
